<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Depth Estimation | Vassilis C. Nicodemou</title>
    <link>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/tags/depth-estimation/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/tags/depth-estimation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Depth Estimation</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/media/icon_hu_5b01a3c72805cea.png</url>
      <title>Depth Estimation</title>
      <link>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/tags/depth-estimation/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refraction-Aware Structure from Motion for Airborne Bathymetry</title>
      <link>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/publication/makris-2024-refraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/publication/makris-2024-refraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this work, we introduce the first pipeline that combines a refraction-aware structure from motion (SfM) method with a deep learning model specifically designed for airborne bathymetry. We accurately estimate the 3D positions of the submerged points by integrating refraction geometry within the SfM optimization problem. This way, no refraction correction as post-processing is required. Experiments with simulated data that approach real-world capturing conditions demonstrate that SfM with refraction correction is extremely accurate, with submillimeter errors. We integrate our refraction-aware SfM within a deep learning framework that also takes into account radiometrical information, developing a combined spectral and geometry-based approach, with further improvements in accuracy and robustness to different seafloor types, both textured and textureless. We conducted experiments with real-world data at two locations in the southern Mediterranean Sea, with varying seafloor types, which demonstrate the benefits of refraction correction for the deep learning framework. We made our refraction-aware SfM open source, providing researchers in airborne bathymetry with a practical tool to apply SfM in shallow water areas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integration of Photogrammetric and Spectral Techniques for Advanced Drone-Based Bathymetry Retrieval Using a Deep Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/publication/alevizos-2022-integration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/publication/alevizos-2022-integration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shallow bathymetry mapping using proximal sensing techniques is an active field of research that offers a new perspective in studying the seafloor. Drone-based imagery with centimeter resolution allows for bathymetry retrieval in unprecedented detail in areas with adequate water transparency. The majority of studies apply either spectral or photogrammetric techniques for deriving bathymetry from remotely sensed imagery. However, spectral methods require a certain amount of ground-truth depth data for model calibration, while photogrammetric methods cannot perform on texture-less seafloor types. The presented approach takes advantage of the interrelation of the two methods, in order to predict bathymetry in a more efficient way. Thus, we combine structure-from-motion (SfM) outputs along with band-ratios of radiometrically corrected drone images within a specially designed deep convolutional neural network (CNN) that outputs a reliable and robust bathymetry estimation. To achieve effective training of our deep learning system, we utilize interpolated uncrewed surface vehicle (USV) sonar measurements. We perform several predictions at three locations in the southern Mediterranean Sea, with varying seafloor types. Our results show low root-mean-square errors over all study areas (average RMSE ≅ 0.3 m), when the method was trained and tested on the same area each time. In addition, we obtain promising cross-validation performance across different study areas (average RMSE ≅ 0.9 m), which demonstrates the potential of our proposed approach in terms of generalization capabilities on unseen data. Furthermore, areas with mixed seafloor types are suitable for building a model that can be applied in similar locations where only drone data is available.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to infer the depth map of a hand from its color image</title>
      <link>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/publication/nicodemou-2020-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://users.ics.forth.gr/~nikodim/publication/nicodemou-2020-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present the first direct approach targeted explicitly on human hands that infers depth from monocular RGB images. We achieve this with a Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) that employs a stacked hourglass model as its main building block. Intermediate supervision is used in several outputs of the proposed architecture in a staged approach. To aid the process of training and inference, hand segmentation masks are also estimated in such intermediate supervision steps, and used to guide the subsequent depth estimation process. In order to train and evaluate the proposed method we compile and make publicly available HandRGBD, a new dataset of 20,601 views of hands, each consisting of an RGB image and an aligned depth map. Based on HandRGBD, we explore variants of the proposed approach in an ablative study and determine the most accurate one. The results of an extensive experimental evaluation demonstrate that hand depth estimation from a single RGB frame can be achieved with an accuracy of 22mm, which is comparable to the accuracy achieved by contemporary low-cost depth cameras. Such a 3D reconstruction of hands based on RGB information is valuable as a final result on its own right, but also as an input to several other hand analysis and perception algorithms that require depth input. In this context, the proposed approach bridges the gap between RGB and RGBD, by making all existing RGBD-based methods applicable to RGB input.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
